[Music]
do
good evening good day everyone wherever
you are in the world welcome to the 72nd
episode of ask a budget this is the last
episode of this year
and it's great to see you all let me
just greet you all i can see cherry
adjacent
uh
and lots of other people
great to see you all great
so as you know today is a live chat
session i am going to be taking your
questions from the live chat so i am i
hope that you are all ready
with whatever questions you have and
then let's get going let's get right
into it
so before i go into that i i just
discovered something new today i
discovered that there is a new theory of
the audience it is called the aryan
refugee theory so apparently the aryans
came into india as refugees
and there are many more theories you
know aryan invasion theory aryan
migration theory aryan tourism theory
aryan picnic theory
and then what else can we think of
aryan continental drift theory
aryan
visa on arrival theory rn student
exchange theory
aryan uh alien invasion theory
uh it's just fun
right so let's take some questions let's
take some questions
um something that we haven't taken
before
is the ancient verna system justified
listen
there is no justification or anything
for in society things just evolve the
way they do
there is no functioning society without
a hierarchy you go to any place in the
world in any period of history any epoch
of history you will always find that
society is stratified it is it has a
hierarchy you have people who do certain
it's called division of labor
essentially you know
but in the case of india it is all
demonized as if no other society has a
division of labor or or or
hierarchy i mean without a hierarchy you
cannot have a functioning organization
you have hierarchies in the army you
have ir hierarchies in corporate
in businesses
in the corporate world you have
hierarchies in any society on the planet
at any given time even in small tribes
you have hierarchies so you know what
all this it's just a waste of time
to to wonder if it is justified and
whether we were evil and our ancestors
were oppressive
come on enough of this
it's it's it's the same old rigmarole
that goes on and on and on and on and
all we do is keep on doubting ourselves
in our history and our ancestors let's
move beyond this and uh
you know move forward
okay
okay gupta and rajendra one word known
as the napoleon of india in south india
while napoleon was born much later
chanakya was the makya valley of india
why because of eurocentrism
the europeans
see themselves as a center of the world
right
i mean how many battles did napoleon
bonaparte win how many wars did he win
and can we even compare that with
samudragupta and rajyandra chola can we
even compare that i mean samudragupta
was the hero of a thousand battles his
entire
life was one extended military campaign
right and rajendra chula i mean his
accomplishments are far greater than
those of napoleon but the europeans the
western world they see everything from
their own little perspective and that's
why they give their little epithets to
our people i mean who was machiavelli he
was a nobody compared to vishnu gupta
chanakya what what are machiavelli's
accomplishments he wrote a book a little
book the
prince he did not administer an empire
he was not the mentor and guide to the
emperor of an entire subcontinent
machiavelli is a nobody
you can't compare vishnu gupta chanakya
with this little insignificant
individual called machiavelli and
similarly samudragupta was far greater
than napoleon so was rajendra chola
and they had even they had better
motives than napoleon napoleon was
anyway so so that's the thing right
there's no comparison so it's all
because of eurocentrism and there's no
need for us
to uh
fall into that trap we should not call
uh samadhika the napoleon of india
there's no comparison
why do historians deny any possibility
of a lost ancient ice age civilization
they don't deny it but we don't have
evidence for it and in in some cases yes
we know that uh history is often
distorted
when it comes to india when it comes to
other places it's uh
there's a lot of eurocentrism there's a
lot of bias and all that
so we do find these uh
these attitudes among historians
especially western historians if you
look at the uh the attitudes they've had
with respect to the history of the
americas the pre-columbian history they
call it of the americas those are very
regressive and
dogmatic rigid attitudes cahokia first
they call it cahokia first as if nothing
was there before cahokia
they claimed that there was no human
inhabitation in the americas before
about thirteen thousand fourteen
thousand years before today which is a
joke
there's already evidence of much older
than that so you know there is this
attitude you know very very rigid
dogmatic attitude group think and
the refusal to to even accept uh
i mean archaeological evidence is facts
and it's something that transcends
uh
history it it this is an attitude that
you find in other disciplines as well
even in even in science you will find
such regressive attitudes for instance
we can give the example of what's that
name arthur eddington was it who tried
to to derail subramanyam chandrasekhar's
career by saying that black holes simply
can't exist there ought to be a low
against a star behaving in such a manner
so these attitudes are quite prevalent
in multiple disciplines
especially among the western
eminent
uh academicians
especially when it comes to
uh work done by people from other
countries especially non-white countries
and so on so you have these things right
so this is all dogmatism it's all
eurocentrism
unfortunately it um facts are facts and
how long will you suppress facts right
okay okay let's get some more questions
goa inquisition i've spoken about it
okay a hypothetical question
if hypothetically the taiwanese
government was in power in mainland
china
what might be their stance towards the
tibet arunachal pradesh in south china
sea and other chinese claim regions
i would imagine that their
stance would be exactly the same as that
of the chinese communist party
because if you look at the official
stance of the of the
taiwanese government
they
do
themselves
claim
arunachal pradesh and tibet as part of
china
so there is not much of a difference and
that's why i i find it quite curious
that indians are so much
are so supportive of taiwan you know
taiwan is not our problem
it is it is okay to use taiwan if
possible as i stick to beat the chinese
communist party with
but there is no need for indians to be
in love with taiwan and consider them to
consider taiwan to be our blood brothers
you know it's not the case
they themselves have the same attitudes
expansionist attitudes it's just that
they are very weak right now and they
are being bullied by the chinese
communist party and maybe they will be
taken over soon but
so so that's the
official stance that they have
all right um
what's my view on the autobiography by
3m who is 3m
do you think fireball from the sky was a
spaceship could you be more specific sir
who is 3m i'm not really sure in which
fireball there are fireballs in the sky
like every week
that we
that we observe you need to be more
specific sir i would like like i'd be
happy to answer but please be more
specific
okay
[Music]
let us
okay this again i think i've answered
this but why is hitler bad and churchill
okay for the western world how can one
counter the claim that churchill was a
hero by publishing facts by speaking
about facts hitler was evil and so was
churchill there's no difference between
hitler and churchill they had the same
attitudes the same policies the the
hitler killed jews churchill killed
indians he
is responsible for the
for the deaths of
at least four million indians i would
say it must be closer to 10 million
because you cannot trust british records
when it comes to the number of people
that killed in india
the official statistics of the bengal
famine are about three to four million
indians died those are british figures
those are lies those are
those are
there is under reporting of deaths
i am sure at least 10 million indians
would have died because of the famine
and because of the diseases and
epidemics that plagued the region
as a consequence of the famine and the
malnutrition
so this was all deliberately engineered
by churchill it's a crying shame that
the west still
kind of
treats churchill as
a hero the british consider him to be
the greatest briton
it's monstrous the guy was a monster how
can one counter the claim talk about it
speak about it tweet about it write
about it in social media our authors
need to write about this
right we need to publish articles about
this condemning
the
uh
actions of winston churchill that's what
needs to happen
okay
why can't the british people
why why didn't the british people occupy
nepal they chose not to they used nepal
as a buffer state
to
to cushion themselves to to to buffer
themselves from the chinese influence
which was uh there was a certain amount
of chinese influence in tibet at the
time and they wanted
they wanted a buffer state in between
that's why they used nepal as a buffer
state it's not like nepal was fully
independent
the gorkhas fought for the british
didn't they they still fight for the
british uh if you look at the incident
in julian wallabag
who was firing the bullets
so that that tells you a thing or two
about the relationship between the
british and nepal
it's like officially it was not occupied
but the nepalese did have to do whatever
the british told them
yeah so that was a situation
okay let's see something else what do i
think happens after death i haven't the
least closer
i don't know uh
i'll let you know someday
okay why don't we see the yeti because
there's no evidence of it it may be
hidden it may not exist
the yeti may either be hidden very well
or maybe the ethic doesn't exist maybe
it's just
people
seeing bears or something like that and
it looks like something different you
know
so there's been this legend of this
beast living in the himalayas for a very
very very long time the british have
reported about that about it the
tibetans speak about it the bhutanese
the security speak about it there is an
entire highway in india that passes
through yeti territory apparently and
yet nobody has been able to capture one
alive capture and or find a dead body of
a yeti
or even take a photograph of a video or
a video of yati so maybe it doesn't
exist maybe it's just a hoax
or maybe it's very well hidden that's
what i can say
these are the the possibilities right
why is indian punjab not known as east
punjab like west bengal
okay so
we call bengal west bengal as opposed to
east bengal which is bangladesh
so why isn't indian pajam known as east
punjab well i don't know
it's up to us to call it whatever you
want to call it for instance you have
this region called northeast india which
is not northeast it's actually the far
east of india it's not in the north it's
it's the far east of india just as
gujarat is the far west of india or
cinda balochistan as the far west of the
indian subcontinent that way
the so-called northeast is actually the
far east of india but we call it the
northeast because the british used to
call it you know how the name northeast
came came about it's because it's to the
northeast of bengal
and the british used to call it the
northeast of bengal but the indian
indian politicians and historians
started calling it just the northeast
so that's how these silly names come
about the northeast is actually the far
east of india similarly you can call
indian punjab whatever you want to call
it you can call it east punjab if you
wish
for us it's just punjab because it's
it's the part of punjab that we have
and
hopefully in the future punjab will be
reunited with india the entirety of
punjab which which is a different matter
so it's it's just semantics
okay let's see some other questions
how efficient is the plan to cut china
out in the malacca
strait the strait of malacca if they try
to acquire arunachal
okay so let's go to the map and find out
where is this place called malacca so
let me share
here we are
so this is the map what is the malacca
strait it's not the creek of malacca
it's a strait of malacca this here
this region here if you can see
this is the malacca strait it's a very
narrow
strait
between these two islands of indonesia
and it's a choke point
so if you want to send a ship into the
south china sea or from the indian ocean
into the philippine sea and the pacific
you have to go through the malacca's
trade
right and the vast majority of all the
uh trade
that happens between
china and the western
the country that are the west of china
it happens through the malacca strait
so the thing is the the the concept is
that india the indian navy could very
easily
blockade the malacca strait
and thereby cut off all supplies to
china if need be
it's a very good plan
if you have a powerful
navy if india has would have a powerful
navy it could easily
blockade the malacca
choke point
and
cause a big problem to china
so by
having a powerful navy india can make
china behave in the north in tibet
by being powerful in this in the indian
ocean
so it's a very good strategy but for
that you need to have a
really powerful navy right now the
indian navy is essentially a glorified
coast guard that's all it is
that's what it is you know just to be
brutally honest and frank i know lots of
people are gonna say no you're wrong no
you're wrong you are
misplaced and your your
contention is incorrect and all that but
no
the indian navy is not powerful enough
right now
india needs a much more powerful navy
and powerful what do what is the what is
the measure of the power of a navy how
how do you measure the strength of a
navy you don't measure the strength of
the navy
of a navy by the number of ships it has
if you look at the indian navy it has a
decent number of ships but out of all
those ships how many warships do we have
not too many how many destroyers does
india have how many corvettes how many
frigates
how many missile boats does india how
many submarines
the numbers aren't very
flattering unfortunately
right and what is the strength what is
the measure of the power or the strength
of a navy it's not the number of ships
you can place on the water it's the
number of missiles you can deploy at sea
on any given day
that is the measure of the strength of
the navy
and well i don't have the exact numbers
but i can assure you that the japanese
navy is way more powerful than in indian
navy when it comes to the number of
missiles that can deploy at any given
time at any given point in time
the japanese navy is more powerful than
indian navy even though japan japan is a
little country
right india has a much bigger coastline
a much bigger
area of interest it india keeps saying
that the indian ocean is our strategic
backyard but slogans
will not make the indian ocean our
strategic backyard we need a much bigger
much more expanded navy we need
what's called distributed lethality
in the in the indian ocean
we need at least at least 50 submarines
we need at least 100 destroyers and
other ships of that kind we need lots of
missile boats
we need to have at any given point in
time at least a thousand missiles
anti-ship and other missiles out at sea
at any given point in time that's when
you become a naval superpower and that's
when you acquire the name the ability to
choke off the malacca straight at any
given any any time of your choosing and
the chinese never won't be able to do a
thing about it
right now the chinese navy is soon going
to be in a position
to bully the indian navy in the indian
ocean itself
the chinese are churning out warships
like sausages
numbers it's all about numbers
quantity has a quality of its own
and i don't know what the indian
planners are doing
so so that's the problem right now so so
you may disagree with me some of you you
may say that indian navy is very strong
and all listen it's not i'm not and this
is not a criticism of the
valor
and the courage and the skill
of the
personnel of the indian navy all i am
saying is that we need
many more warships
india needs to start constructing
warships on a war footing india needs
many more submarines that's when you
become
a
great power right now india is not
so
so that's what it is
india has been the most invaded country
why did we not build a wall on our
western border like china did to fend
off the mongols
you know the chinese built a wall and it
had no effect on them on the mongols
the mongols just swept past the wall
the wall had was was
it was not able to save china from the
mongols
you know a wall does nothing
when you have technology of all is just
like it's it's it's pointless
so that's why
when you have an efficient military when
you have the right strategies and
tactics
walls do nothing
you can have a city with huge walls
very good anti-siege defenses and yet
you can be besieged and
and cracked open
so in
as as technology uh progresses as
technology advances as new tactics and
strategies uh coming to come into
existence these old tactics of building
walls they become completely pointless
and india is such a large large
subcontinent you'll have to build a wall
that's thousands of kilometers long
it'll be a multi-generational project
and yet it wants a really uh safeguard
you from the invaders so so it's it's
not pre it's not really practical
and
so that
i suppose that's why a wall was never
built or never even thought of
right
um
[Music]
there were lots of sudden invasion
inventions at the time of the world war
do you think there was any alien
intervention at the time you know when
you have a war it is
essential
to uh develop new technology to in order
to prevail especially when you have
something like a
very major conflict like a world war so
you have to start churning out new
technology in order to gain the edge
over your adversaries
and that's why
the military is always the the
the
domain from which a lot of new
technology emerges which eventually
makes its way into the civilian sphere
lots of spin-off technologies you will
get eventually a few years few decades
down the line in the civilian sector
which all originated in the military
domain
so these inventions they happen out of
necessity
out of a desire to survive and to
prevail there's no alien intervention
that we know of
i mean
thus far in the entire recorded history
of humankind there is not one single
proven
alien encounter there are all kinds of
claims there are all these videos around
but they're all pixelated grainy black
and white or something nothing is ever
something that is unambiguously true
so you know
um so one has to be very skeptical when
it comes to these alien claims it's nice
fun i mean i'll be the happiest person
if there is an actual proof
of
an alien visitation
to our planet but thus far i have not
been able to find anything that is
unambiguously true
and therefore i can say that there was
no alien intervention at all
right
history of santa
no i'm not an expert in the santa
business so
uh i have some
rough idea but yeah let me not go into
that because i i may be wrong
and it's it's not something that i've
ever been really interested in so
so yeah i'm gonna have to pass on this
one but
nice
okay what else do we have
okay let's see what this is hershey says
as of now we have good relations with
countries like the us
france israel
should we convince them to use the real
map of india including p o k and c okay
what's my opinion in this my opinion is
very clear
we can use any map we want but as long
as the facts on the ground are the facts
on the ground
people will use other kinds of maps
what india needs to do is not to try not
convince people to use a different map
india needs to change the facts on the
ground
the fact is that these territories are
illegally occupied by other countries
and as long as that situation
exists
other countries
will draw maps that reflect that
situation
so convincing people to draw a different
map and all that is an exercise in my
opinion in my opinion it's an exercise
in futility what india needs to
work on
is to
redraw the maps on the actual ground and
change the facts on the ground so that's
what india needs to do
okay what else do we have
i can see what went wrong with bihar
what went wrong with bihar is what went
wrong with the rest of india
the foreign invasions and the foreign
occupation of india
that's what what went wrong with bihar
bihar was one of the greatest
regions of india i don't know when this
name bihar came into existence it was
typically uh in the past known as
magadha wasn't it the capital was partly
putra which is now known as patna
so it is one of the
we could say
in some sense it's the heartland of
india
right
it was the the seed of great empires
uh the mauryan empire
had its capital in patliputra
the
gupta empire sprang out of magadh it
also had its capital initially in
patliputra
so bihar was
one of the greatest regions of india it
produced so many great people
so what happened was that it was
destroyed during the colonial era
during the turkic occupation of india
and later in during the british
occupation of india the turks what they
did was they destroyed all the
universities all the cultures all the
temples etc
and they installed their governors to
to ruin the state to ruin the region
further and then the british took over
and this was simply flattened everything
they destroyed everything whatever was
left so that's what happened that's what
went wrong with the state of bihar after
independence after the transfer of power
of 1947 you know how the country has
been mismanaged misgoverned and ruined
further so so that's what happened it's
the people of bihar may not realize this
they are the descendants of some of the
greatest people who ever lived in this
country
so
and and it's it's because they're not
taught this
right like you say it was the one of the
wealthiest culturally rich and greatest
regions of india abundance of intellect
and all that
so the people of bihar need to
need to be made aware of this that there
is a great deal of greatness in this
region and in their
ancestry and one hopes that bihar will
regain
its lost glory in the future
soon in the future i hope
okay
physics
astrophysics what binds the galaxy
together is it the supermassive black
holes at the center are they so powerful
to bind the galaxy together why do
galaxies spin
what binds the galaxy together is the
force of gravity gravitation
according to the classical theory of
gravity the newtonian theory of gravity
uh
all masses attract each other by the
inverse square law
right and that's what happens so when
you have a collection of massive bodies
like stars etc
then they will all clump together and
the
very fact that they all come together
imparts a certain spin
to the body which is the galaxy and yes
they do most galaxies have a
supermassive black hole at the center
which kind of also uh
helps in binding the galaxy together
so
it's just the fact that you have gravity
the force of gravity which which uh
causes galaxies to
to be bound together you also have these
globular clusters of stars you have
dwarf galaxies you have
super clusters of galaxies as well it's
all because of the force of gravity that
these structures are bound together
and this pain is because of the movement
i mean
when two
bodies
uh they experience the force of gravity
they move towards each other so there's
a motion in in place and when you have a
whole bunch of such bodies which move
towards the
common
uh center of mass then it's going to
typically create this uh spinning motion
that's why every single galaxy you will
find it's it spins every solar system
every stellar system spins that's why
every planet rotates every star rotates
that's just the way
the universe is
okay what else do we have why is there
no mention of foreign civilizations or
cities or people in mahabharata
because india was the only civilization
at the time
we have to understand what a
civilization is a civilization is
different from a kingdom
or from a city or a tribe or war all
that a civilization essentially is a
large geographical region with a single
culture a single connecting language
single cultural or civilizational
language
and it has
a great deal of prosperity great deal of
organization it is under one political
typically typically under one political
power
of course a civilization can have lots
of kingdoms within itself
but it's typically one single culture
one cultural or civilizational language
and all the institutions are governed by
the same cultural norms and the values
of the entire civilization and it's a
region of great prosperity and stability
good standards of living all that is
characteristic of a civilization so
india
in the old days was the only
civilization
that most likely existed there was
nothing else
apart from india from a civilizational
perspective there may have been other
tribes other nomadic peoples other
kingdoms here and there but no
civilization
right
so that is indeed the case
all right um
domi her i don't know what that is
what's the point of having a hope for a
better life in kali yuga is there a
point of continuing the civilization in
this yoga well you have two options
either you continue or you stop
it's your choice
it's like uh
it's like
why what's the point of living
is there a point of continuing this life
you know the
the purpose of human life is to try and
keep on making progress
we don't know the real purpose of what
life is like and what is the
deeper philosophical spiritual meaning
of existence is there life after death
is there rebirth is the reincarnation do
the gods exist
we don't know but we have to try and
live the best possible life that we can
and we have to try and keep on
we have
keep alive the endeavor to make the
world a better place
that's what
gives you some hope and purpose in life
otherwise you have this
some people have the nihilistic mindset
that everything is pointless everything
is worthless why live and why be moral
let's be amoral let's indulge in all
kinds of uh
immoral activities why why work hard
let's go and sit and smoke and drink and
all that you know
so that
what what that ends up doing is that you
end up living a worthless purposeless
life
and there is no happiness or joy
or meaning in such a life
right
so it's it's up to you of course
it's your personal choice but from my
perspective
one must as long as one keeps drawing
breadth one needs to try and keep
working towards making the world a
better place and working towards make
making one's life
uh productive purposeful
and something that is valuable to
society into the world at large
okay
um
an axis victory in the second world war
have benefited india
what role would sebastian rabos have
played in such a scenario well it
depends on how
mr bose would have played his cards
so if there was an access victory in the
second world war it would have it would
essentially mean that the japanese would
have been able to
successfully invade india and defeat the
british
in that case
what would have been the fate of india
is the big question
uh after that would mr bose have been
would he have succeeded in
in either evicting the japanese from
india
or ruling india in in in some kind of
alliance with japan
these are all hypothetical questions
but uh had the access powers won it
would all have boiled down to mr subash
bose's ability
to do what was best for india because
the japanese were the the
japanese were ruthless they were quite
brutal
and
the way they treated indian prisoners of
war was also quite brutal the way they
the kind of atrocities they perpetrated
on the andaman in in the andaman nicobar
islands also is a chapter of history
that has been kind of forgotten
so
had the japanese prevailed i'm not sure
if they would have allowed mr bose
to
establish an independent government in
india they would have either appointed
tried to
make him play the role of a japanese
suzerain a puppet of sorts and if he had
not been inclined to do that maybe they
would have
sidelined him eliminated him perhaps and
put somebody else in place
so yeah it's all hypothetical but
even
an axis victory would not possibly have
been very good for india
unless the unless the germans also got
involved so there are all kinds of
hypothetical scenarios and parameters in
there
but the best possible thing that should
would have happened was that the
japanese lost and subhash bose won that
would have been the ideal scenario for
india in which case india would have got
real
genuine independence free from the
british free from the congress free from
all the all the but liquors of the
british that would have been the ideal
scenario but as we know that did not
happen unfortunately
many jain scholars say that jainism is
older than hinduism is it true
see i have not heard of any jain
scholars saying this and
there is no difference between jainism
and hinduism jainism jaina dharma is one
of the philosophical schools of thought
of sanatan dharma it falls within the
umbrella of sanatana dharma therefore
there is no difference between jainism
and hinduism
right
ah how
does katherine the great translate
bhagavad gita
i don't know
i haven't heard of any such thing
very interesting question but
unfortunately i don't have the answer
as far as i know there was no connection
i'll see
um
if we make a time machine will we be
able to travel before the big bang
well first of all there is no way to
make a time machine there is nothing in
the laws of physics that says that we
can have a time machine
and there is no technology that exists
that
could
possibly take us further forward or
backwards in time
and the funny thing is that even if such
a technology was possible if you went
backwards in time you would end up in
empty space
because
the earth is constantly moving in space
if you go back in time
you're gonna be stuck in a point in
space where the earth wasn't there at
the time so you know
it's all nice uh from the perspective of
science fiction and all that but it
it's not really
possible in the real world and even if
such a machine were possible i don't
think it's possible to go beyond the
confines of the universe that we are
part of so no even if a time machine
were were to be possible
we would not be able to travel before
the beginning of the universe which is
the big bang
okay um
who was giordano bruno why did the
priests kill him brutally
did he know something which offended
them jordana bruno was a
monk a christian monk
in europe he was all clearly
clearly italian
and he is somebody who went beyond what
was acceptable in christian doctrine
so he speculated that there must be
other words out there he i think he said
some certain things that were considered
to be heretical i don't remember exactly
what he said but the kind of speculation
most likely which he did was that the
earth is not the center of the universe
and there are other earths out there on
which there are other people in that
sort of thing
i think that's the kind of that's the
kind of statements he made and that's
what he's what he really believed and
maybe he also believed that there is
divinity in all plants animals other
things not just humans
which kind of goes against the one book
one god one prophet thing that
you know which they have
so i think initially he was persecuted
he was excommunicated exiled or whatever
but he did not stop
so eventually what happened is that they
burnt him alive they burnt him alive
that's what they did
did he know something that offended them
no it is not the knowledge that he had
he had no special knowledge knowledge as
such
but the views that he held and the views
that he communicated openly
were heretical views these are views
that the church found extremely
dangerous because it would make people
believe that god is is attainable to
everyone with or without the church
think about the church is that
they had this strangle hold on the
people of europe
and
according to the doctrine the church
doctrine the only way i mean first of
all all humans are born sinners so you
are by default going to hell
but if you
live the kind of life the church orders
you to live
then
before you die a priest may forgive you
or give you absolution or or or shrive
you or something like that and it is
only through the path of the church that
you can go to heaven
and that's what the church is the all
powerful body and that sort of thing so
and and you are essentially a sinner and
there's only one god out there in heaven
there's no god anywhere else
and jordana bruno was kind of i think he
was of the opinion that there is
divinity in everybody so that is
deep deep heresy so that's why they
they
killed him by burning him at the stake
so that's the that's the story roughly
about jordan bruno there may be some
some
some small changes here and there
but i think i got the overall story
right
okay uh
what else do we have
is it true that the red fort of delhi
was made by maharaja anangapal ii i am
not really very sure
not really sure there are clearly uh
older
older fort structures in delhi
uh the fort made by prathiraj johan is
also there i am not quite sure about the
red fort was it made by bharajan paul ii
it
may possibly be the case but i am not
100 sure i think i will have to look
this up
and
ask me this again next time i hopefully
will have a more definitive answer to
this
interesting question
prakriti says what would have happened
if there are no black holes with
cleopatra no what
what would have happened if there is no
black holes in the universe
my opinion on cleopatra
did akhinathan have indian genetics what
is the death ministry of nana's oh my
goodness how many questions have you put
in this
okay if there were no black holes in the
universe the universe would have been a
very different place
so it is it is most likely that in the
very early universe
there was this overproduction of
microscopic primordial black holes
because of quantum fluctuations
if that did not happen then the universe
would have been a very different place
maybe there would have been no galaxies
because these primordial black holes are
believed to have become the eventual
supermassive black holes and they
uh
are what kind of uh
made galaxies clump together so if there
were no black holes then it would mean
that the laws that we have in the
universe would have been different
because black holes were created black
hole production happened because the
laws the physical laws of the universe
have have a certain shape and form
and if no black holes were there in the
early universe or the
present day universe that means the laws
would have been different so it would
have been a very different universe
my opinion on clear butter great lady
eknathan did he have indian genetics i
think many of the pharaohs
ha of
of of of egypt
had indian origin genetics r1b i believe
i think tutankhamun
had the r1
was a member of the r1b haplogroup which
is a descendant of r1 which is a
descendant of r which is a descendant
eventually of the haplogroup f which are
all indian origin haplogroups which is
very interesting
death mystery of nanasia i'm not quite
sure unfortunately i'm not very sure
about that
all right
um
what's happening between russia and
ukraine is the world war iii inevitable
see nothing is inevitable the russians
nobody wants war these are all
these are all games on the geopolitical
chess board of the world
mr putin
is
making a certain play right now a
geopolitical play
russia is currently not a very big
economy as you know it may not be even
in the top 10 economies of the world
right now but it is a
genuine
military superpower it has the biggest
nuclear arsenal in the world it has a
very big geography its economy is
dependent on
on gas
on gas and other
exports
and the thing is that
there is
a danger that the
russians may get overwhelmed by either
the us or the chinese so they are making
their presence felt in europe
and they are being encircled in europe
by nato to a certain extent
there are nato missiles pointed at
russia from close to the russian borders
so the russians are applying pressure on
ukraine because ukraine is leaning
towards nato so there is this entire
situation that's happening right now
so mr putin may either possibly see we
don't know what's going on in the head
of mr putin mr putin will never let
anyone know what he's thinking so there
are certain options either mr putin
genuinely wants to
invade
ukraine and annex the territory so he
will do it if he has calculated that
there will not be any major
repercussions
or
he is pressurizing nato he is
pressurizing europe he is showing the
european union that they are powerless
to stop him
right he's raising his geopolitical
profile
and becoming one of the three major
geopolitical players in the world
he
may be telling the us that i am open to
negotiating with you
he also wants to offset china so there
are a number of possibilities
and
different scenarios at play right now we
don't quite know what it is
i am not in the game of making
predictions whether it's going to invade
or not but i can guarantee one thing he
doesn't want world war three
world war three will cause untold
destruction
it will destroy the russian economy the
chinese economy the american economy and
other economy as well nobody wants that
sort of catastrophic war
so everybody knows
more or less what the red lines are and
one plays within that in geopolitics
all right all right all right what do we
have what else do we have
what are my views on the methane kingdom
of syria i have a couple of videos about
the methane it's it was a great very
interesting uh
kingdom
they were of indian origin the the
notable thing about the methane kingdom
is that their aristocracy the royalty
was of indian origin they spoke
late vedic sanskrit
the common people spoke the hurian
language i believe but the aristocracy
spoke sanskrit which means that the
methane kingdom was ruled by
the the aristocracy was indians who had
migrated westwards from india
this is about
three and a half thousand years before
today
so these i mean
these are the facts i don't have any
specific views i can tell you what the
facts are
i i think i've spoken about this
multiple times in the past so maybe you
can check out some of my earlier videos
and you may get more information from
there
all right
um
what else do we have
why don't we change the wrong history
taught in the textbooks well the
textbooks are
in i mean they they are uh
they the writing of the textbooks
changing of textbooks etc it's all
something that the government needs to
do
i
what we can do as individuals is we can
write our own books but those won't be
adopted as textbooks in ncert or any
other school board college board
university board
so the official textbooks if you want to
change them the government must do that
the government must take the initiative
so for whatever reason that is not
happening right now so
one hopes that in the future sooner
rather than later there will be some
progress in that direction because
clearly our history is greatly distorted
okay or ryuzaki says how japan being a
dharmic country was so adamic and
ruthless in world war ii
it's because of the meiji restoration
so there was this event in japan called
the meiji restoration the meiji emperor
of japan in the middle of the 19th
century
he uh
unleashed this revolution of sorts
he called it it's called the meiji
restoration so what he did was he tried
to turn japan into a copy of the west
he tried to westernize japan thoroughly
he tried to eradicate buddhism from
japan
and this
attempt failed
he tried to wipe out buddhism and make
shinto the state religion of japan that
failed it did not work
but what he did succeed in doing is to
uh
is to essentially uh destroy the primacy
of the samurai warriors of japan who
were typically the chatriers of japan
they were staunch buddhists the samurai
so he uh made them powerless he ended
essentially he destroyed the institution
of samurai
and he adopted a complete western system
in the governance in the armed forces in
the bureaucracy and everything else
so he tried to completely westernize
japan he was against buddhism he was
against dharma the people continued to
follow buddhism
japan is still you could say to a large
extent
buddhist shinto
intermixed
syncretized but the major emperor of
japan a dharmified himself
right so he stopped following the
precepts of dharma and the japanese
imperial
dynasty kind of continued that after his
death
so in world war ii
even though japan was a dharmic nation
the governance the military etc was
completely westernized and it was
completely adarmic
and that's why they took those they did
those things that are so
barbaric and brutal the kind of things
they did in nanjing the
nanjing in china the the treatment of
the chinese whom they they conquered
china the treatment of prisoners of war
and all the other atrocities they
perpetrated japanese soldiers it's
because they abandoned dharma
right
so people have asked in the past that if
if
asian empires were dharmic and that's
why
they they did not do certain things like
colonization and so on why did japan do
that during the second world war it's
because they had abandoned dharma that's
why they tried to conquer and colonize
the whole of asia and there the kind of
atrocities that perpetrated were well
terrible absolutely terrible
in china in korea other places as well
so that's an interesting question that
you've asked
okay what else do we have
okay pratyab energy says who are these
so-called techs geographically where
do are they originally from please show
in a map
as you say sir or ma'am whatever
so this here is the map as we know
over here
in western asia we have the nation of
turkey
so who are the turks the turks are the
descendants of the ancient hunnic people
of
eastern asia
the
the hornet people
uh they are recorded about two and a
half thousand years ago the chinese
called them the show new people
so the hunnic peoples
were the ancestors of the mongols as
well as the turks
initially the turks followed the same
culture the same
religious practices as the mongols
tangorism it's a polytheistic
we could say religion if you want to
call it a religion
so the origin of the turkic people
is somewhere in this region can you see
my mouse pointer here
this is mongolia so it's somewhere here
in eastern asia
and it is uh
maybe somewhere here so if you look at
this entire region eurasia then most of
eastern russia what is now russia most
of it is
inhabited by people who speak turkic
languages all of it the entirety of
siberia essentially is inhabited by
turkic speaking people
so there's this big turkic diaspora in
this entire region
it all originated
somewhere in this region somewhere here
the gobi desert the the plains of
mongolia
northern present-day china
so this was the original homeland of the
hunnic people
and it is from the hunnic peoples their
descendants were the mongols and the
turks the mongols remained in mongolia
and the turks they spread across
eurasia
and they displaced and kind of wiped out
the skittions
from central asia
so that in brief is the story of the
turks and eventually they
they invaded eastern greece anatolia
which is now called turkey
so that in brief is the story of the
turkic people
all right
um what else do we have why don't some
indians why do some indians not want to
go out of bharat
i think it's a matter of personal choice
some people want to go out and travel
maybe some people want to go and settle
somewhere else some people want to stay
in india i think it's a matter of
personal choice you will have to ask
them
i don't i am not privy to everybody's
to what's what goes on in people's minds
but
it's a mixed bag
have i had any paranormal experiences
not really
not quite really
okay um
what else do we have
the future of gaming in india sangeeta
says asangat asks
i think gaming has a bright future in
india i think lots of
kids lots of teenagers are
quite fond of gaming
so uh
gaming is something that is catching on
you also have these esports and all that
you have the playstations the xboxes
you have
pc games
esports and all that so there's a lot of
interest in gaming especially among the
so called generation z the zoomers yes
and
in the future you may even see game
development happening in india which
would be a very welcome step there are
already some games that have been
um
that have been created in india with
with indian cultural themes and all
maybe one or two games like that so
maybe that might take off in the future
so i think there is a good feature of
gaming in india
it's certainly something that is going
to take off it looks like
all right um
what else do we have what else do we
have
what are my views on the dinosaur embryo
found in china
is there any chance that china is aiming
to do anything else using this embryo
thing i think it's nice they found
i i heard they found a very well
preserved
embryo inside a dinosaur egg that's what
i heard i'm not very sure about all the
details about this
what are my views i think it's a great
thing
the chinese are
investing a lot of
time money effort all that in
paleontology
and that's paying off so it's good
what else can they do with this embryo
thing i am not sure they can do anything
beyond
study it properly and put it in a museum
and display it i mean what else can you
do with an embryo a dinosaur embryo so i
guess that's that's the extent to which
they could do something
okay rodra says can we change our dna as
shown in
ben10
being transformed into entire new alien
body using the dna
how much of it is true or is it possible
in the near future ben 10 is some anime
series is it
i suppose i've heard something like
most likely anime
so listen
what they show in anime serials and uh
in science fiction is all science
fiction it's it's very dangerous to try
and play with human dna human dna is
incredibly complex and we don't
understand more than three four percent
of it
we don't understand more than three four
percent of human dna there is this
so-called dna dark matter that we don't
understand at all there are so many
sequences we don't know what they code
for and you know what more than 50 of
human dna is of viral origin ancient
viruses that combine with us and so on
there is so much we don't know about it
and some people are using crispr to
change certain things they don't know
what are going to be the consequences of
this
several generations down the line it's
very dangerous
to start playing god and changing dna
and all that you know
so
and and
if you want to transform into an alien
body you will first need to know what
kind of
dna an alien body would have and we have
no alien bodies at our disposal that we
can examine and see what sort of dna
will be there so
it's not possible not in the near future
maybe not even in the far future why
would one want to do this first of all
why would somebody want a different kind
of body
so you know it's it's uh
all right now in the realm of science
fiction it is very dangerous to
try and alter dna without fully
understanding the repercussions
so i don't think it's going to be
possible in the near or even the
moderately distant
future
okay i am asked the kalpa vigraha
question so many times i don't know much
about it unfortunately
i've tried looking for info see this
question here
i have tried to look for the kalpa
for information about this so-called
kalpa vigraha idol idol
i haven't found any any definitive
information about this idol i mean what
is the evidence that is this this much
these many years old and where is this
idol found
i think it's some kind of a metal idol
metal structure
metal
metal murti of something
there is no way you can date a metallic
object
if it's an organic thing with carbon we
can date it using carbon dating
but a metallic object how do you know
how old it is you can't really tell
so i i don't know much about this
unfortunately i don't have enough
information do holes exist we don't know
we have never observed any but
hypothetically they could
all right what else do we have
oh man
who are the true audience first of all
so clearly shubham you you seem to
believe that white people are audience
right that's what you think
i think i have to explain this in every
single session that the only people who
can genuinely be called aryans
or indians
or the iranians or our
close relatives iranians nobody else can
be called aryans white people european
people are not aryans
the true aryans are indians you shubham
are a true aryan
all indians and all iranians when i say
indians i mean the entire indian
subcontinent we are the true aryans
nobody else is an aryan europeans are
not aryans
germans are not aryans greeks are not
aryans only indians and iranians are
aryans the kalash people are indian
that's why they are true aryans just
like the bengalis just like the
sinhalese just like the kashmiris just
like the marwaris
just like the odias
just like the pashtuns
just like the persians just like the
balochis these are all the real aryans
everybody else are fake aryans the
germans are fake aryans europeans are
fake they're not aryans
end of story
okay
um what else do we have
can entertainment like cinema and video
games boost a country soft power yes it
can see japan
see how popular japan is see how much
people admire japanese culture see how
cool they think japanese culture is it's
all because of cinema video games and
anime
right
so yes you're right it certainly can
boost the country's
soft power
google maps is fake
russia is oversized africa is much
bigger
why are they not changing it there is
how is it the the the challenge is this
uh it's not fake it is what you will see
on every map
the challenge the problem is that you
have to represent
a three-dimensional sphere
on a two-dimensional surface
and that's why you have all these
distortions yes you're right africa is
much bigger
and russia is oversized if you look at
the globe if you look at the map of the
world on on an actual globe you will see
the real dimensions and the real
contours of the continents
but if you
project the three-dimensional sphere on
a two-dimensional surface it is
inevitably going to throw up distortions
i think this is called the mercantor
projection if i'm not mistaken or
something like that
so it is not fake
it is as accurate as you can possibly
make it
and it's just the problem is that you
cannot
accurately represent a three-dimensional
surface
object on a two-dimensional surface
you will have to distort some parts of
it
but you know what it's a good
observation that you have made most
people are not aware of this so very
good observation sir
my thoughts on vogue culture i have
spoken about this at length you can
check it out in my previous videos one
of my previous videos one of the short
clips i'm sure i have it
um
parito says my opinion on the people who
claim that they have spoken to aliens
met aliens
other things watched ufos
well
you know what
i
i am a big skeptic
when i was a kid i was so
interested in ufos i really wanted ufos
to exist and aliens who have visited the
planet but as you grow up you you come
face to face with reality
and i have not seen a single proven case
a single case of an alien visitation
alien encounter
ufo whatever you call it a single case
that can be proven without doubt
so these are just claims people claim
they have seen ghosts i have never seen
a ghost
right
so people make all kinds of claims maybe
they genuinely believe that they have
met
aliens but then can you please
show a video of you talking to the alien
or a photograph selfie
selfie with you and the alien or some
evidence that
we can actually see and
believe no
so i am very skeptical about this
i am sure some people actually believe
it that it actually happened but
unfortunately none of them is ever able
to produce any
real evidence
so what can i say
hmm
um what else do we have what else do we
have
peter projection
okay
uh okay what else do we have what else
do we have um
[Music]
how can we change the world's view on
the swastika
it's bad image made by the nazis by
speaking the truth and by
by
by reclaiming the swastika all of us
so i have answered this question more
times than i can remember
superior culture doesn't mean superior
military
if you have a great culture great
civilization and if you don't take the
military measures to defend your culture
and civilization then what's the point
of having it
what's the point of having great
monuments great temples great culture
great civilization if you will no and in
the richest country in the world if you
don't build a powerful military that can
safeguard it
so when we talk about superiority
we're talking about civilizational
cultural superiority
right and wealth
but unfortunately we lacked political
unity when the turkic invasions happened
and that's why we were not able to
defend ourselves
and of course we had certain
certain
kings
who forgot
or disregarded
the teachings of vishnu gupta chanakya
and that's why we lost
so that's what happens
um
mr singh says how do you see the hindus
of pakistan
any specific role you see we can provide
in the revival of bharat love from now
pakistan
nice to
have a hindu from pakistan over here
we wish you the best what are my views i
think the hindus of pakistan are
terribly oppressed
they are undergoing an active genocide
we know what's happening to the
unfortunately to the girls and and women
in the hindu community of pakistan they
are being abducted you hear these
reports almost every day of a pakistani
hindu girl being abducted and married
off to some pakistani person
and the state the establishment is
actively complicit in all this in
allowing this to happen it's it's
terrible it's terrible
so what can the pakistani hindus do what
role can the pro can they play in the
revival of bharat
unfortunately as of today what what role
can the pakistan hindus play they're
power powerless right now right
so i think it is for india to find a way
to somehow
safeguard
the interests of pakistani hindus which
is not happening right now many pakistan
hindus are coming to india as refugees
and they are living in terrible
conditions in india
so i think as of today because of the
complete powerless
state that pakistani hindus are in i
don't think they can play any real role
in the revival of bharat
the revival of bharat will have to
happen first from bharat from within
bharat itself
and once bharat is revived enough strong
enough powerful enough then it can take
care of the interests of pakistani
hindus and all pakistanis who are all
victims of what's happening there
so
so i certainly um
wish
the pakistani hindus all the best for
sure
okay
what was the purpose of the acropolis
what do people do there exactly
what is the purpose of the acropolis
today it's a tourist
spot it's a tourist monument people go
there and take selfies and take pictures
and take drone videos and all that
what was the original purpose of the
acropolis it was some kind of temple to
the greek gods i don't remember which
god or goddess it was
was it one god or goddess or was it
multiple gods and goddesses that were
that were worshiped in the temple i
don't remember i'm not quite sure but it
was a greek
temple to
to
one of the greek gods goddesses or
multiple that's all i can say
okay what else do we have
lots of questions
what did people use to light fire before
matchbox and lighter
somebody had asked me that
i remember seeing some questions some a
couple of days ago
that
the matchbox was invented by european so
how did indians celebrate diwali before
the matchbox was invented
you know there are lots of ways of
lighting a fire
there are many there are many techniques
that you can use
you would consider some of these to be
primitive techniques
but do you know that the gunpowder was
actually invented in india not in china
gunpowder
which is the integral component of the
match box
was invented in india the invent it's an
indian invention
it made its way to china the europeans
saw it in china first so they say the
chinese invented gunpowder which is
nonsense
it is an indian invention and since it
was invented in india i am sure we had
something other which which
uh which used gunpowder as a means of
lighting small fires controlled fires
must have been there unfortunately we've
lost
a lot of this information
but
india was the greatest civilization in
the ancient times and i'm sure they had
lots of different ways
of lighting fires
i have answered this question in great
depth multiple times what do i think
about brain drain
going to western countries for better
living standards income
well people do what people have to do
unfortunately in the past 70 years there
has been a very big
scarcity of jobs and everything else in
india so people
whenever they could they moved out of
india there was nothing they could do
patriots were not welcome in india
talented people were not welcome in
india india was the india still is the
nation of very low standards
india is still a nation of mediocrity
the indian establishment loves
mediocrity
the indian education system loves
mediocrity the indian education system
specializes in identifying talent and
destroying it it specializes in
promoting mediocrity identifying
mediocrity and promoting it that's the
kind of
system the naruvian regime created and
the other subsequent regimes
kept on uh promoting
so people had no option anybody
who had any talent and had any ambition
in life were forced to move out of india
and yes that is what causes the brain
drain that's what causes the brain drain
india is losing all its not into other
countries you can see how many indian
origin ceos you have in the west in the
us and other countries
right
doctors ceos
engineers
entrepreneurs startup founders
silicon valley
so much more
so yes we are losing our best talent to
other countries because the indian
system even today
even today is a system of mediocrity
go to any iit you will see that their
conference rooms and washrooms
are state of the art best in the world
they have invested crores of rupees in
their conference rooms
and in their washrooms now go to the lab
in any iit
you will find all equipment is 20 30
years old
everything is absolute so how do you
expect the iits to do any world-class
research today and see the attitude of
the professors the majority of them
there are obviously some good
individuals some good professors but see
the attitude of 90 of the professors
they are they have no interest in any
progress any development
any research
go to any university in india you will
find the same thing it's a country of
mediocrity it's not a country of
mediocre people the governance
and the establishment
values mediocrity
right so that's why people are forced to
leave
you can't blame them
hopefully in the next few years we'll
see changes
uh one does see some small signs of
changes here and there but overall the
system is very mediocre and people don't
realize that we are
a nation of very low standards
we are a nation that tolerates failure
a nation that tolerates failure among
its leaders and most of our leaders not
all most of them tolerate failure among
their subordinates
so it's a country of very low standards
unfortunately so that's why people who
have ambitions people who value
themselves they
they have no option but to leave the
country even if even though they may
actually love the country
so that's what i can say about this
right
a presidential system would be a good
change
it would certainly be better than the
current system we have
okay how many questions
how did scientists take a picture of the
milky way galaxy so we are inside the
milky way galaxy so we cannot take a
picture of the milky way galaxy from
outside
we can only see the shape of the galaxy
from side on and we can only guess at
the size and the shape of the galaxy we
know the size of the galaxy we know that
it's more or less a spiral galaxy but we
don't have the exact details because we
are we are inside it right
so the pictures we take of the galaxy
are not the kind of picture you would
see of the andromeda galaxy or the
sombrero galaxy or other spiral galaxies
right
is it true that time flows differently
in the quantum world we don't even know
if time has any meaning in the quantum
world right we use time as an external
parameter in the quantum world
as as
when you see the schrodinger equation
there is uh the
the uh derivative with respect to time
but we are using time over there in the
classical sense not in not in a quantum
sense we're using time as an external
classical parameter in quantum mechanics
but does
does time have an actual quantum meaning
we don't know
does time even exist in the quantum
world we don't know is it something that
emerges out of the quantum world we
don't know does time flow in the quantum
world
uh
these are
questions that haven't quite been
answered thus far
yeah so so
can't really answer
we do use time in in the quantum world
in the schrodinger equation
and so on
but it's still an external classical
concept if you know the difference
between the classical
world in the quantum world
right what else we have
we see mohandas gandhi's photograph on
all our currencies can we change it to
other people like nitaji listen if i
were in charge of the currencies i would
change it
but we are not in charge of it
i don't know who's in the rbi is it the
government of india i'm not sure who
makes these decisions
they are the ones who can change it we
cannot change it we the people we the
people are powerless in this so-called
democracy
right
we the people are actually powerlessness
in this
democracy we don't really have any
decision making ability
right
um
krishna mohan
says has britain fought an unjust war
against the maratha empire
if not how come the marathas who drove
out the mughals failed against the
british in the third anglo-maratha
what could be unjust in a war
there is no justice in a war a war is
not a
a contest of who is just and who is
unjust
right
there is no morality or ethics in
warfare
it's all about winning
there is no unjust war
war is war
so the british were foreign occupiers
who did not believe belong in india but
they had superior firepower superior
tactics superior strategies
and the marathas unfortunately
um
because of a variety of reasons they
lost eventually to the british there is
nothing unjust in a war
right
there is nothing see
money
isn't good or bad money is just money
it's its value
it's it's a measure of value
power isn't good or bad it's just the
measure of the strength that you have
right
similarly in in war you use these things
these tools
and whoever wins wins there is nothing
right or wrong just or unjust fair or
unfair the only objective in war is to
win
okay what else do we have
is the concept of rebirth rebirth
scientific it's not a scientific concept
it's a philosophical or spiritual
concept it is not something that is part
of science because we have never
observed
evidence i mean there is no way of
proving that rebirth happened
there is no scientific way of proving
that rebirth happened because the
rebirth is the
uh
it is the soul being trans migrated from
one body to another after death
taking place or taking both a new body
but this concept of the soul itself is
an unscientific concept it is a
philosophical and spiritual concept it's
not a scientific concept why do i say
it's not a scientific concept because
science is concerned with
observable
phenomena
measurable phenomena and the physical
world
the soul is not a physical object it is
a spiritual object right so
that's why this is not a scientific
concept it's a philosophical or
spiritual
concept
don't get sick says how does curse work
i don't know
i may not be the right person to i
certainly am not
the right person to ask this question i
don't know how curses work
all right um
what are my views on a certain person
views don't matter man views don't
matter
facts matter
what do you think is the likelihood of a
hindu state separating out of india
would you entertain that why or why not
the likelihood is that hinduism will
become extinct in the next 50 to 100
years
a hindu state separating out of india
hindus are not hindus have never been
separatists right
hindus consider india to be their
homeland why would hindus want to
separate out of india a separate hindu
hindu state
i think the likelihood is
extraordinarily low like one in a
billion
so
that's what i can say
all right um
uh what else do we have
were the shudra is actually not allowed
to study in the ancient guru system
please read the work of
what's his name the beautiful tree
the beautiful tree who's the author i
forget the name of the author
darampal read his work and he will get
the answer this is not this is not true
all right
um
there is plenty of evidence for life
after life life after death i hope you
mean
please see is there life after death
moderated by john cleese what do you
mean by evidence what is what what
constitutes evidence
the question is in science
in science
what constitutes evidence
when someone comes and claims oh this
has happened does it mean that this
evidence that is the kind of evidence
you have in a court of law that this
person has made a claim
in science evidence is measurable
and observable
right
i am sure many people have made claims
and you may be interpreting that as
evidence that is not evidence in the
world of science
in the world of science
evidence is something that is observed
and measured
by multiple independent observers and
multiple independent experiments
that is how it works in science
so
people will make movies documentaries
discussions they will have all kinds of
people who may come and make claims that
is not scientific evidence
it does not constitute evidence in
science
right
so that's what i can say i am i know i
am aware of lots of people having made
this claim
that there is a rebirth and this once a
person was
has been rebirthed reborn as a child and
he or she can remember everything from a
past life okay fine
but still it does not constitute
it does not represent scientific
evidence it simply
claims that people are making
can you tell about the vaka tech dynasty
i think i will have to make a detailed
video about that it's a very interesting
dynasty
very interesting phase of indian history
it's the kingdom was almost like an
empire it was quite big
so i think i will i will take that up
separately it's a very long
so it's not something i can explain in
like 2-3 minutes
but it is certainly something i will
take up properly in detail in the future
the answer to this is no
um
uh the virus will keep evolving do you
think humanity is gonna end soon i don't
think humanity is going to end
see viruses
they keep evolving you're right
and the purpose of a virus is to survive
that's how you evolve you don't evolve
in a way that will kill you if a virus
keeps killing the human host the virus
itself dies
the virus doesn't it will evolve in such
a way that it will become less harmful
to humans
we have all heard of the oh micron
variety of the virus right
it is a less deadly form of the virus
but it is more transmissible so that is
how virus evolves
it changes
in such a way that it will cause less
harm to the host
and it will be more transmissible so
after o micron whatever next comes will
be even more transmissible and even less
deadly so humanity is not going to end
soon this is not a danger very dangerous
virus i know it kills some even the flu
virus kills people right
obviously are we thinking that humanity
will end zone because of the flu virus
every year there's a new variant of the
flu which comes out right
doesn't even bother
the thing the thing is that this virus
is going to become
is going to become less deadly and may
be more transmissible it's not going to
cause
big problems
to humanity
uh how did the did the old indian
education system promote or allow
hitting students by teachers
it is considered unethical these days i
think this entire practice of hitting
students came with the catholic
schools i think even today in catholic
schools and convent schools and
missionary schools it is a common
practice to
to beat children
to beat children with sticks or rulers
or whatever
i don't think it was there in the indian
education system the pre-colonial
education system it's a characteristic
of the um
british
system and the
christian system
if you watch the
what do you watch
there's the song by pink floyd
um
another brick in the wall we don't need
no education all that see the video
there's this english school master
school teacher who's hitting students
with a stick
so that's a british and christian thing
it's not an indian thing
i heard that hindu is not a foreign term
it is written in the rigveda and other
ancient scriptures no it's a foreign
term
indians never call themselves hindus
the term hindu came from from the river
sindhu
which is the
which is called indus in english
or our parsi friends the persians
our persian cousins
they pronounced words differently their
language was almost the same as sanskrit
but they pronounced words differently so
instead of sir they said ha
so instead of sindhu they said hindu
and that's how
this word originated
and then this region became known as the
hindu region to the persians
and then they started calling indians as
the people of the hindu region
and then the turks and the arabs also
picked up this practice
so it's an exo nym it's a word used by
foreigners but now indians call
themselves hindus i mean now it is it is
used for the people who uh
follow the ancient
culture
and uh civilization and religion of
india which is
they're called hindus now so that's what
happened it is not something that came
out of indian
literary texts and religious texts
sacred texts
what is my opinion on gender fluidity do
you think gender and sex are separate
see i am very clear about this a person
who has two x chromosomes is a female
a person who has one eye x chromosome
and one by chromosome is a male
that's a simple definition of male and
female these days everything is a social
construct gender is a social construct
everything is you know this work
nonsense is is ruining the western world
it's best we don't get into all that
right
so that's my opinion but
i don't even know what gender fluid it
is
i mean do you keep trans migrate trans
transforming from one gender to another
half the time you're male after time
you're female two day morning i was male
tomorrow evening i'll be female does it
work like that really
come on
all right
um what what do we have
okay let's see this rajkumar says
if in the future i will take control of
the asi or open my own archaeological
service society
will you be my guide oh yes certainly
please do it and contact me i will be
your guide sir and i wish you the best
i i hope that you succeed in this
endeavor of yours
all right um what else do we have
you said there was no evidence for jesus
but what about mentions by tacitus and
josephus i haven't seen these
mentions by testis or josephus what i
said is that there is no archaeological
or any other
evidence of jesus the same whether there
is no archaeological or other evidence
of alexander people have made all kinds
of claims
but where is the archaeological evidence
see it is the same line of argument
that the west uses for the ramayana and
the mahabharata where's the evidence
unfortunately now there is
archaeological evidence for both these
eras of india's history both these
events
but where is the archaeological evidence
for alexander
or jesus archaeological hard evidence
not people making claims tacitus
josephus olivias anybody can make any
kind of claim i don't care about
people's words i want to see our hard
archaeological evidence
where is it show me
there is none
neither for alexander nor for for for
jesus
okay what else do we have
what's the geopolitical advantage of the
andaman islands why isn't the government
putting efforts to use it in the
advantage the andaman islands give us a
brilliant
staging
place
for all kinds of activities in the
indian ocean region it can if we have
naval bases air force base is there we
can easily choke off the malacca malacca
strait
it's essentially an unsinkable aircraft
carrier we can use it like that
why isn't the government doing whatever
well we need to ask the government
we
i cannot answer on behalf of the
government right
so i would certainly advocate
using the
andaman islands
as
as a military base
for the army air for the air force and
for the navy as well
it would be very beneficial
for india geopolitically and militarily
all right
how do we differentiate between right
and the wrong information
how to identify the right source of
information how to okay okay let's let's
take one thing inside i'll take the
first question
how do you differentiate between right
and wrong information you do it if you
have sufficient knowledge otherwise you
will never know which information is
right which information is wrong
you may trust people
that you feel are
some is someone who gives you the right
information but that is a matter of
trust and faith
but even
somebody whom you trust may perhaps
be wrong in something
so you will not be able to tell unless
you yourself have sufficient knowledge
so the best way
to equip yourself to be able to
differentiate between right and wrong
information
is to become
knowledgeable and well informed yourself
which is a long process there is no
shortcut to this unfortunately
unfortunately
okay where do what else do we have
what is my name
um
your name is what i see there what does
it say
okay what else do we have
um my thoughts my thoughts about the
james webb space telescope
did you see my yesterday's live stream
is the first question i took
the james webb space telescope it if it
succeeds
if it
if it performs as we expect it to
then it's going to open up a whole new
window into the universe it's going to
act as a time machine and we will be
able to see the very beginning
of the e of the universe
not the big bang itself but the
births of the first stars the first
galaxies all that but that's still about
six months away
the telescope is right now on its way
towards its final destination which is
in orbit around the l2 lagrange point
and
a lot can go wrong in the way
it's a million and a half kilometers
away from here
from from our planet
once it reaches there it it will
it will be unfolding itself on the way
and
a lot of things will have to go right
for it to be able to function as as
planned and it's a six month long
process and if everything goes well then
it's going to start making the
observations six months from today
so it's a long process
but i hope it succeeds because if it
does then it's going to be brilliant for
us
it's going to
it's going to give us information that
maybe we may not even have imagined
possible you know
so we will learn a lot if it works
okay what else do we have we have lots
of repeated questions
um
uh what else do we have what else do we
have
uh karthik says india and china got
independence around the same time
then why is it that china is ahead of us
economically militarily
global impact etc
because they they
because we had naru the naruto regime
and later regimes that simply did not
care about the development of the
country
and the chinese communist party was
interested in developing the country and
becoming a superpower two completely
different trajectories until the 1990s
both countries were almost equally poor
and then the chinese went upon embarked
upon this project of modernization of
everything
and
as you can see it has worked and india
is still
plodding along
now i think hopefully hopefully
hopefully things will change for the
better in the next 20 years but just see
the history and say you can see why they
might happen because our leaders
our leaders were not were not interested
in bringing india out of poverty so it
actually
may be the case that they wanted to keep
india poor
you know so that's why
predates the concept of photography
but the most but the first successful
method of photography was the
daguerreotype
it follows the same principles did india
know it before did indians know it
before
i don't know
unfortunately i don't know anything
about this
okay
because we have nehru and they had mao
that is indeed the case actually mao was
not very good for china mao zedong
um he did consolidate the
this triangle hold
of the chinese communist party on on
power in china
but the kind of reefs if you would call
them reforms they were in many ways
catastrophic for china the so-called
great leap forward caused the deaths of
millions of chinese in in this
artificial famine
uh the four pests that he went after the
sparrow
the sparrow what else was it
the rat was it there were some four
pests i have spoken about this before i
don't remember that what exactly the
four pests were
then there was the so-called cultural
revolution that again caused so many
deaths so mao zedong
he did uh establish
complete control over china
but
his actions were disastrous for china it
is later on
the actions of then shopping essentially
that set in place
set into motion the process of china
rising out of poverty and becoming a
genuine global power mart did indeed do
certain things that were good for china
such as
his emphasis on developing a chinese
rocket program space launch program
using technology borrowed from russia
from the ussr which in turn had been
borrowed from the nazis and so on so
yeah you know it's a long story but
the two nations went on completely
different trajectories the chinese
wanted power they wanted power on a
global stage
and mr nahero
well he was mr nehru
all right
okay what else do we have um ding
shopping is the best and biggest leader
for china i think he's the one who said
set in motion all the big reforms
that have made china what it is today
for sure he is the best leader they have
had in the past um since the chinese
communist party took over i am sure mr
xi jinping would disagree with that
but
yes it is then shopping who is
responsible for
the rise of china
all right where are we what else do we
have
uh i don't even know what an anu
anunnaki is
i've heard this term lots of times i've
been asked questions about this i don't
know what an annunaki is
so
sorry i can't answer
okay can two or more planets have the
same orbit around their star it is
certainly
possible i'm not sure how stable such an
orbit would be in the long run
for instance we have
we have the lagrangian points so one of
the lagrangian points is is in a
straight line from the earth and the sun
but on the opposite direction so you
could certainly have a stable orbit
there
so it is theoretically possible for two
two planets
to be in the same orbit around their
star
two
i don't think more than two
most likely it's just two i think there
are two lagrangian points that would
allow you to have the same orbit there
is another
there are a couple more i think there
are total of four lagrange points out of
which two are of the same orbit so i
think two planets can
have the same orbit at the same time
around the star but in different
locations
are you a superhuman no sir i am not
superhuman i am an ordinary human
very much
ordinary human
uh have you read autobiography
autobiography of a yogi
if if you read it then how was it
i have read the book more than 15 years
ago i don't remember much about it
yeah so i'm not sure what to say because
i don't remember much about it it did
not make a very big impression upon me
that's what i can say
okay
why don't you write books on indian
history
okay
uh how to retain information
how do you retain everything i read i do
not retain everything i read i i just
told you that i read that book
autobiography for yogi and i remember
next to nothing about it
there you go that's the secret
what is the secret
the secret is when you read something
give yourself permission to forget
if you read
with the mindset that you it is okay to
forget what you don't find interesting
then you will automatically remember
whatever you find interesting
you see a book can have lots of things
that you may not find interesting what
is the point in remembering such things
you should only remember
things that interest you
so the way i read is i am perfectly
willing to completely forget everything
what i'm reading i will only remember
remember what i found interesting
intriguing fascinating everything else
will just be
discarded from a memory so that is how i
read
i have read so many books
i don't even remember the names of the
books people ask me for book references
i can't remember because i've read so
many books and much of what i have read
i have deliberately forgotten
because it was pointless
there's there are many books
that are good
but even the good books have some
information that
may not be very useful you know
so that is how i approach reading i read
a lot i read very very fast
and i remember what i find interesting
everything else i forget so that's how
you should also try and approach things
give yourself permission to forget
then you may actually end up retaining
more
alright let me take one more question
didn't i answer this i think i did
um
[Music]
okay roshan
roshan says
please answer this all right sir i'll
answer it what's the question please
shed some light between the history of
nepal with context of india
also how come both the countries are
separated when so much is common the
nation
system is a very recent invention it's a
european thing
india has historically been a
civilization state nepal has always been
a part of india
right when you look at the mauryan
empire which is an indian empire wasn't
nepal part of the mauryan empire
during the time of chandragupta maurya
during the time of ashoka the great
if you look at the kushan empire which
was an indian empire was it nepal part
of the indian empire the kushan empire
if you look at the gupta empire
wasn't nepal part of the gupta empire
under kanda gupta
under kumara gupta
have you heard of yashod dharman the
great king of
nepal was part of his empire as well
so nepal has always been a part of india
i don't
you know
people will keep claiming things that we
are a separate country yes you are a
separate nation state which has been
created very recently
but the territory of nepal the geography
of nepal has always been part of india
it's part of the indian subcontinent
it's part of indian civilization the
nepalese people have the same blood same
culture same custom same civilization
same languages as the rest of india
end of story
so why did the country separate because
the british kept this country separate
nepal as a buffer state between india
and tibet that's the long and the short
of it
is gravity the strongest force no it's
the weakest force
okay
and is there anything else
should india leave the commonwealth
nation group is any or anything
significant is left in the commonwealth
group like trade or fdi there's no point
being part of the losers club
the commonwealth of nations is the
losers club the countries that lost
britain and were occupied and colonized
and destroyed by britain
why does india need to be part of this
nonsense
it is the losers club india should leave
the losers club that's what i would say
if india has any self-respect india will
lose will leave it
all right i think we are at the end of
today's session so
thank you everybody for
all your questions
this is going to be the last ask a
widget live stream of this year
so i would like to take a moment to
thank all of you
this channel was
a tiny small baby channel a few months
ago now it is
a small to medium sized channel all
thanks to you it is growing quite fast
because of your viewership
i am very very immensely immensely
grateful
for the privilege of your viewership
i'm very honored
i am blessed by the gods and the gods
are you all
so thank you very much for everything
and we're gonna continue next year
and we're gonna keep going
so
enjoy the rest of the year and i will
see you in the new year until then take
care
thank you again and i'll see you soon
bye